(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-09-01T16:52:28.220928",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
皆さん、こんばんはー！ハロー！
Good evening, everyone! Hello!
こんばんはー！こんばんはー！
Good evening! Good evening!
ということで、
So today,
まず自己紹介からやっていきましょう。
let's start with self-introductions.
ホロライブの清素担当、みんなのアイドルの夏色まつりです！
I'm Matsuri Natsuiro, Hololive's pure idol!
今日はMC、よろしくお願いします、頑張りまーす！
I'll be your MC today, please treat me well! Let's do our best!
じゃあ今日参加してくださるね、人たち一人ずつ行きますよ。
Now, let's go one by one with the people participating today.
じゃあ、よっぴーからお願いします！
First, Yopi, please!
はーい！イオフィリア、オブイサ、どうもです。
Hii! Ioforia, Obuisa, hello.
ホロライブインドネシアから、イオフィです！
I'm Iofi from Hololive Indonesia!
今日はあの、まぁ、トペを、ちょっと、えーと、のことをちょっと、勉強したいと思います、よろしくお願いします！
Today, well, I want to learn a bit about onomatopoeia, so please treat me well!
お願いします！
Please!
じゃあこぼちゃん！
Now, Kobo-chan!
わかわかわかわかんないよ！Your service, let me be your Santa, Santa in your day.
I don't know at all! Your service, let me be your Santa, Santa in your day.
わかんないよ、連ちゃんにしそう。
I don't know, it sounds like consecutive answers.
今日はオノマトペや、えー、勝ちだ！お願いします！
Today is onomatopoeia, um, winning! Please treat me well!
がんばれー！
Good luck!
じゃあ続いて、ジジ！こんばんは、ジジです！
Next up, Gigi! Good evening, I'm Gigi!
ジモニ、えっと、日本語ちょっと上手くない、え、あの、まだまだペ、え、ちょっと、え、日本語頑張って！頑張ります！
Jimin, um, my Japanese isn't very good, um, still, um, Japanese, do your best! I'll do my best!
ありがとう、頑張って！上手上手！
Thank you, do your best! You're doing great!
じゃあ続いて、ホモJPのペーちゃん。
Next, Holo-JP's Pe-chan.
いやいやいや、我々はカオス！ホロライブの白衣ベルズです。
Oh no no no, we are chaos! I'm Hakos Baelz from Hololive.
今日は翻訳担当で、え、やりたいと思います。よろしくお願いします！
Today I'll be in charge of translation. Please treat me well!
お願いします！
Please!
じゃあ最後が、ラオーラ。
And lastly, Raora.
こんにちは！ララ・パンテーラです。
Hello! I'm Raora Panthera.
今日は、えっと、英語書いたり日本語で話したり頑張りまーす！
Today, um, I'll do my best writing in English and speaking in Japanese!
はい、お願いします！
Yes, please!
上手ー！
Great job!
お願いします！はい、可愛い！
Please! Yes, cute!
ということでね、本日はですね、皆さんにおノマトペクイズに答えてもらいます。
So today, everyone will answer an onomatopoeia quiz.
あの、ちょっとね、日本独自の表現とかもたくさんあるんですが、頑張って答えてね。
Um, there are a lot of uniquely Japanese expressions, so do your best to answer.
あの、是非日本に、あの来る時はいっぱい使って頂きたいなと思います。はい、ということで、
Um, I hope you'll use them a lot when you come to Japan. Yes, so,
早速第1問行きましょう！
let's go straight to the first question!
おい！クエスチョン、クエスチョンわー！
Hey! Question, question!
えー、クエスチョン、このオノマトペは何を表しているでしょうか？え、コケコッコー！
Um, question, what does this onomatopoeia represent? Kokekokko!
はい！ワツディス、ザサウンドオフ？コケコッコー！
Yes! What is the sound of? Kokekokko!
ウェア・ドゥ・ヒア・ディス・オン・ア・マタポイア・フロム？ポイユア？
Where do we hear this onomatopoeia from? Puyua?
あー、わからない！
Ah, I don't know!
あ、待って...
Ah, wait...
あれ？私なんで？え？おかし... おかしい？
Huh? Why? Wait, is this... Is this right?
ケッコッコ... ケッコケッコケッコ...
*Kekkokko*... *Kekkokekkokekko*...
ペンが... おかしい。
My pen is... acting weird.
あれ、なんでこんな... ケッコケッコケッコ...
Wait, why is it like this... *Kekkokekkokekko*...
書けるかな？
Can I write with this?
ちょっと待ってください、アプリ再起動します。
Hold on, I'm restarting the app.
Should we draw?
You can do whatever.
I just draw it.
I drew 'cause I don't know what it is in Japanese.
It's alright.
I don't know the word.
あ、待ってください。はい。
Ah, hold on. Yes.
書けるかな？... 書けるかな？
Can I write?... Can I write?
あ、書けます。あ、よかった。
Ah, I can. Oh, great.
終わった。
Done.
コケコッコ... コケコ...
*Kekkokko*... *Kekkoko*...
声に出したら分かるから...
If you say it out loud, you'll get it...
コケコッコ... コケコッコ...
*Kekkokko*... *Kekkokko*...
遠い... 大丈夫か...
Far... Is this okay...
コケコッコ... コケコッコ... ですよ。
*Kekkokko*... *Kekkokko*... you know.
オッケー、じゃあ一人ずつ聞いていきましょう。
Okay, then let's go through them one by one.
じゃあよぴぴ、何だと思いましたか？
So Yopipi, what did you think it was?
あ、チキンです。
Ah, it's chicken.
あ、チキン！はいはいはい。
Ah, chicken! Right, right, right.
はい、じゃあえっとこぶちゃん。
Okay, then next is Kobo-chan.
Ah, before, I was thinking about frog, but I think kekkokokko...
It... It sounds like Indonesian, koko royo!
So it's chicken! Oh, なるほど！
So it's chicken! Oh, I see!
なんか、もともとカエルだと思ってたんだけど、なんかインドネシアのオノマトペでも...
I originally thought it was a frog, but even with Indonesian onomatopoeia...
オノマオノマオノマ... オノマトペ... オノマートペ... オノマートペッ...
Onoma-onoma-onoma... onomatopoeia... *onomatopee*...
にわとりの音に似てるので... 似てるね、チキン。なるほど。
It sounds similar to a rooster's sound... It does, chicken. I see.
えー、ケケケ、ケキョココ。英語は... cock-a-doodle-doo! Chickenね。
Uh, *kekeke*, *kekyokoko*. In English, it's *cock-a-doodle-doo*! Chicken.
cock-a-doodle-doo! ああ、なるほど。同じだね。
*cock-a-doodle-doo*! Ah, I see. It's the same.
あ、僕も... 鶏。あ、チキン... だと思います。
Ah, I also think it's... a rooster. Ah, chicken.
For me, it's like a bird that is screaming likeoko! Like, 'I'm here!' and...
For me, it's like a bird that is screaming like *koko*! Like, 'I'm here!' and...
koko? koko? 'I'm here!' and maybe he wants food in his mouth...
...because maybe it's small, you know? I don't know.
Wait, what do you think it is? A bird?
Bird? 叫びとり?
Bird? A screaming bird?
鳥の叫びとりじゃなくて、叫びとりね。
Not a bird screaming, but a screaming bird.
なんかお腹空いてる、叫ぶ鳥ね。妖怪？
Like a hungry, screaming bird. Is it a yokai?
じゃあ、正解行きましょう。
Well then, let's go to the correct answer.
正解は、チキン（鶏）でしたー！
The correct answer was chicken (rooster)!
まあ、正解にしますか。叫ぶ鳥だもんね。
Well, we'll count it as correct. Since it's a screaming bird.
鳥、鳥は鳥なんだからね。素晴らしい、鳥は鳥だからね。
A bird, a bird is a bird after all. Wonderful, a bird is a bird.
続いて第2問！え、こちらは動物の泣き声でございます。
Moving on to Question 2! This is also an animal's cry.
じゃあ第2問、こちら、ケロケロ。
So question 2, this one is *kerokero*.
あ、ケロケロ！あ、イージー！イージーイージー！
Ah, *kerokero*! Ah, easy! Easy, easy!
べいちゃん、それは... へえ... へえ？
Bae-chan, what is that... Huh... Huh?
すごい！
Amazing!
え、マイペン？オッケー。
Eh, my pen? Okay.
ワッツ？ケロケロケロケロ... かわいい。
What? *Kerokerokerokero*... Cute.
ケロケロ... ローラ、大丈夫？
Kerokero... Rora, are you okay?
あ、だい、だいじょうぶ。オッケー is working.
Ah, da-daijōbu. Okay is working.
Thank you.
ベエちゃんの... なに？Hold on, I forgot what it looked like!
Bae-chan's... what? Hold on, I forgot what it looked like!
Is that... What are you drawing?
Why is she drawing herself?
ベエがはく... It's like a chimera, you know? じろみみたよ。
Bae is coughing... It's like a chimera, you know? Look at it.
きみら！
Hey, you guys!
ヒマいのやめて
Stop saying we have free time!
おいっじゃ、ちょっと一人ずつまた聞いていきますか
Alright then, let's go around and ask each of you one by one.
かわいいみんな
Everyone's so cute.
えーじゃあ、よぴぴ
Uh, then Yopi-pi.
はい！
Yes!
カエルのプログレス
Frog's progress...
あー、フロッグ、ケロ、ケロケロでしょ？
Ah, frog, kero, kerokero, right?
なるほど
I see.
はい！
Yes!
じゃあ続いてこぶちゃん
Next, Kobu-chan.
私も、かえ、カエル？
Me too, kae, kaeru?
カエル、フロッグ、カエル、はい、ケロケロ
Kaeru, frog, kaeru, yes, kerokero!
すごーい！
Amazing!
祭りもかけないよ、カエル
You can't even write it, frog.
じゃあ続いてじじ
Next, Gigi.
はーい！
Hi!
ケロケロ、ケロピー
Kerokero, kero-pee.
なるほど
I see.
じゃあべーちゃん
Then, Bae-chan.
あ、カエルです。
Ah, it's a frog.
カエルかな？
Is it a frog?
カエル、カエルです、ケロケロ
Frog, it's a frog, kerokero.
ケロケロ、ケロケロ
Kerokero, kerokero.
一瞬ずつつね
For a split second...
一瞬ねずみだと思ったんだけど
I thought it was a rat for a second.
ちょっとね
Wait a second.
だっても、カエル見たことないんで
Because I've never seen a frog.
カエル、カエルがハクバ
Frog, frog is Hakuba...
その隣の、ラウラめちゃいい上手
The one next to it, Laura is so good at it.
かわいい！
So cute!
カエルですね
It's a frog, right?
カエルです
It's a frog!
じゃあケロケロ正解は
Now, the correct answer for kerokero is...
カエルでしたー！
It was frog!
やったー！やったー！
Yay! Yay!
イージー、イージー、イージー
Easy, easy, easy!
日本語上手よ
Your Japanese is so good!
じゃあ続いていきますよ。続いては…
Now let's continue. Next is...
馬の鳴き声は日本語だと何と言うでしょうか？
What do we call a horse's neigh in Japanese?
なんて聞こえるかな？
What does it sound like?
はききていこう
Let's do our best!
一人ずつ泣いてもらうからね
Each of you is going to neigh for us!
じゃあよぴぴから、よぴぴの馬の鳴き声
So starting with Yopi-pi, Yopi-pi's horse neigh.
お願いします、どうぞ！
Please, go ahead!
はききって行こ、です
Let's do our best, is it?
それ、それが違うでしょ
Wait, that's completely different!
馬これしか知らないですよ
This is the only horse sound I know!
薄すぎる
That's way too thin!
馬これしか知らないですよ
That's the only horse sound I know!
じゃあ続いて、こぶちゃん
Next, Kobu-chan.
ひほ、ひほ
Hiho, hiho.
ひほ、ひほ？
Hiho, hiho?
私感じるのが、別の動物じゃない？
I feel like that's a different animal, isn't it?
ひほひほ別じゃん
Hiho hiho is totally different!
ひほ、ひほ
Hiho, hiho.
じゃあ続いてじじ
Next, Gigi.
じゃあ続いてべーちゃん
Next, Bae-chan.
うまー！
Uma!
めっちゃ日本語しゃべるやん
You're speaking so much Japanese!
じゃあ続いて、ラウラ
Then, Laura.
じゃあ正解は、馬の鳴き声って何？
So the correct answer, what is a horse's neigh?
ヒヒーン！でした
It was 'Hihiin'!
ヒヒーン？
Hihiin?
ヒヒーンだったらラウラじゃないの
If it's hihiin, isn't that Laura?
ラウラはリアルすぎかな
Laura was a bit too realistic, huh?
ヒヒーンが、ヒヒーン…あっ最後にんがある
Hihiin, hihiin... Oh, there's an 'n' at the end.
ヒヒーン
Hihiin.
あ、もう配信中？
Ah, is the stream already live?
私のカウント？
My count?
あ、や、ごめんごめん
Ah, yeah, sorry sorry.
ひふー？ひふー？
Hifu? Hifu?
のひふー？のひふーの？
No hifu? No hifu no?
のかんたん？のかんたん、ソーリー
No kantan? No kantan, sorry.
のひふーひふー可愛いけどね
No hifu hifu, cute though.
残念ながら不合格でございます
Unfortunately, it's a failure.
では続いて、えー、今から、えー、ユーチューブの言葉の意味をね、当ててください。
Now next, um, from now on, guess the meaning of the YouTube words.
じゃあ行きます。
Okay, let's go.
ぺこぺこだ〜！の意味は？
What is the meaning of "Peko peko da~!"?
じゃ、よぴぺ。
Now, Yopi-pe.
ハングリーです！食べたいです！プリング食べたいです！ハングリー！
Hungry! Want to eat! Want to eat pringles! Hungry!
食べたいです！ぺこぺこです！
Want to eat! Peko peko!
じゃあ、こぼちゃん。
Now, Kobo-chan.
ぺこぺこ、インドネシア語の意味はラッパーです！
Peko peko, in Indonesian it means rapper!
ラッパーとはどういう意味ですか？
What does rapper mean?
ラッパー？
Rapper?
ラッパーはハングリー！
Rapper is hungry!
あ、ハングリー！ハングリー！ハングリーね、オッケー。
Ah, hungry! Hungry! Hungry, okay.
じゃあ、じじ！じじ、顔だけしか書いてない。
Now, Gigi! Gigi, you only drew a face.
お腹空きすぎた！ぺこぺこだー！お腹空いたね！お腹空きすぎた！
Too hungry! Peko peko da! Hungry, right! Too hungry!
ジジ、可愛い！
Gigi, cute!
じゃあ続いて、べーちゃん！はい、ハングリーです！あれだ、腹ペコ、オッケー。
Now next, Be-chan! Yes, hungry! That's right, harapeko, okay.
じゃあ、ラオーラ！あ、ペリーハングリー！
Now, Raora! Ah, very hungry!
あ、じゃあ全員おんなじだね！全員ハングリー！可愛い！
Ah, so everyone is the same! Everyone is hungry! Cute!
ハングリー、ハングリー！
Hungry, hungry!
えー、ということで、全員正解！やったー！イエーイ！
Um, so, everyone is correct! Yay! Yay!
じゃあ続いて、も、えー、当ててください。意味を当ててくださいね。
Now next, guess this too. Guess the meaning.
チンしてね！の意味は？
What is the meaning of "Chin shite ne!"?
え？
Eh?
チンしてね！チンしてね！
Chin shite ne! Chin shite ne!
ピー・プリーズ？違うの？ピー... チン！
Pee please? Is it not? Pee... Chin!
じゃあ聞いてみますか。え、よぴぺどうでしょう？
Now, shall we ask? Eh, Yopi-pe, how is it?
はい、最初はちょっとドアのベルだったんだけど、あれピンポンだから、チンしたらあの、マイクロ波？あ、マイクロ波！あたためる、そしたらチンってなるじゃん。なるほど。
Yes, at first it was a doorbell, but that's ping-pong, so when you microwave, um, microwave! Warm up, then it goes chin. I see.
じゃあ、こぼちゃんは？あ、あれ？こぼちゃん！こぼちゃん、これは...
Now, Kobo-chan? Ah, what? Kobo-chan! Kobo-chan, this is...
なんか、チンは、ちょっと...！そのものみたい！そのものみたい！チンは、あら！チンプリーズ！チンプリーズ！
Um, chin is, wait...! Looks like it! Looks like the thing itself! Chin is, oh my! Chin please! Chin please!
わかんない
I don't know.
じゃあ次行きますか じじじじ
Well, shall we move on? Ji-ji-ji-ji.
あ わかんない
Ah, I don't know.
ち やばい
Chi-, oh no.
ち やばくない
Chi-, isn't that bad?
やばい ち やばい
Oh no, chi-, oh no.
の やばい やばい
No, it's bad. It's bad.
じゃ ペいちゃん ペいちゃん お願いします
Then, Bae-chan, Bae-chan please.
はい ベニーの チン ですね
Yes. Benny's "chin".
温めてっていうことですね
Meaning "warm it up".
Please go warm it up in the microwave
じゃあ 最後 だから
Then finally, so—
えー わかんない わかんない
Ugh, I don't know. I don't know.
わかんない
I don't know.
I don't know
どうしよう
What should I do?
maybe
あー maybe something like...
Ah... maybe something like...
maybe when when the glass when it touch the glass
Maybe when the glass, when it touches the glass...
ああ ガラスの 音ね
Ah, glass sound, huh.
確かに っていうか
True. Or rather—
な やばい の と やばい ね
No, it's bad. No, it's bad, right?
いや わかんないよ
No, I don't know.
じゃあ こちらはですね 正解は
Well, the correct answer is—
microwave
チーン ご飯を温めてください
"Chin." Please warm up your rice.
あ いいですね、サイレンですね。
Ah, that's nice, a siren.
でもう なんか、warm up food in a microwave、なんちってね
But like, "warm up food in a microwave," you know.
あー、なるほど。例えば、ごはんをこう置いといて
Ah, I see. For example, leaving rice there,
ええ、あとに帰ってきた人、ごはんが冷めちゃってるから「チンしてね」ってメモを残したりしますね。
and when someone comes back later, since the rice has gone cold, they leave a note saying "chin-shite-ne" (warm it up).
おお、なるほど、なるほど。
Oh, I see, I see.
こぼ、こぼチンしてね、チン、チンしてね
Kobo, Kobo, chin-shite-ne, chin, chin-shite-ne.
please warm it up for me. チンしてね。
Please warm it up for me. Chin-shite-ne.
Oh, okay, so if you wanna if you wanna say pee please...
Oh, okay, so if you wanna, if you wanna say "pee please"—
いや、どうやって言うんだ？ I might need that one.
Wait, how do you say that? I might need that one.
ちょ、ちょ、No pee. No, no pee.
Wait, wait, no pee. No, no pee.
じゃ、じゃ、peeはど、ど、ど、ど、ど、どう、どう言ったらいいの？
Then, how, how, how do you say "pee"?
Peeってあれ？ Pee please
"Pee" is what? "Pee please."
おのまとぺあ、Pee please. Pee please
Onomatopoeia. "Pee please. Pee please."
Pee? Peeってさ、おしっこ？
"Pee"? "Pee" means pee?
おしっこ、おしっこ！あ、じゃあ、Sh—
Pee, pee! Ah, then— Sh—
シャー、シャー please!
"Sha-, sha- please!"
シャーシーっていう
"Sha-shii," or something.
シャーおし！シャー、の、の、の、の、の
"Sha-oshi!" "Sha-", no, no, no, no, no!
Noだめね！だめ、だめよ！すみません、シャーおし！
No, that's no good! No, no good! Excuse me, "Sha-oshi!"
だめだめだめ！国民の、おしっこ！
No, no, no! Citizens' pee!
おしっこ、ありがとうございます、分かりました！
Pee, thank you very much, I understand!
やばい！
Oh no!
えじゃあ、Next行きましょう。こちらでございます。
Well then, let's go to the next. Here it is.
「静まり返ったとき」めっか静かなとき使うオノマトペは何でしょう？
What onomatopoeia is used when it gets completely quiet?
What's onomatopoeia that they use when it goes really, really quiet?
What's the onomatopoeia that they use when it goes really, really quiet?
静かなとき
When it's quiet.
静かなときも音がある like when it goes really quiet all of a sudden, what's the onomatopoeia that they would use?
Even when it's quiet, there's sound—like when it goes really quiet all of a sudden, what's the onomatopoeia that they would use?
I'm gonna write the, the onomatopoeia I just learned.
I'm gonna write the onomatopoeia I just learned.
漫画読んだらわかるかもね。漫画に書いてあることもあるかも？ ジャパニーズ漫画。
You might know if you read manga. Sometimes it's written in manga, right? Japanese manga.
what is it like that? Is that how you know it?
I don't know how to spell it.
じゃあ聞いていきますね、よぴぴから。
Then let's ask, starting from Yopipi.
あ、しーん。はい、しーん。多分こうやって、しーん。
Ah, "shi-n". Yes, "shi-n". Probably like this, "shi-n".
はいはいはい。
Yes, yes, yes.
続いてこぼちゃん。しーん。
Next, Kobo-chan. "Shi-n."
じゃあ、じじ。え、しゃー！しゃー！しゃー！
Then, Jiji. Eh, "sha-!" "sha-!" "sha-!"
Isn't that the pee?
What, wouldn't it get quiet after you pee?
じゃ続いたべちゃん。
Next up, Be-chan.
いや、忘れた。なんか…
Wait, I forgot. Like...
あ、すん？
Ah, "sun"?
違う。「すん」はちょっと違うか。「しーん」だったか。
No, "sun" is a bit different. Maybe "shin"?
やっぱ、どっちかと思ってたんだよね。
I was wondering which one it was, you know.
じゃ、どっちだろうな？
So, which one could it be?
あ、みみ？
Ah, Mimi?
うん、Yes.
Yeah, yes.
ああ、いや、I think it's shiin!
Oh, no, I think it's "shiin"!
Like, I remember when I read some mangas, but I might be wrong.
Maybe it's shiin.
漫画に…オッケー、got it, got it.
In manga... Okay, got it, got it.
オッケー。
Okay.
じゃ、正解に行きましょう。
Now then, let's go with the correct answer.
正解は「しーん」でございます！
The correct answer is "shiin"!
やったー！
Yay!
え、ほらほら、ほらほら！が正解だぜ！
Hey, look, look, look! That's the correct answer!
よ、You're so close, Gigi!
You're so close, Gigi!
Gigiの「shiin」、shiin。そう、
Gigi's "shiin", shiin. Yeah,
Nが必要ですね、こぼちゃん。「shin」ね。
you need an N, Kobo-chan. "Shin."
ああ、そうですね！あらららら、shiin、shiin！
Ah, right! Oh my, shiin, shiin!
Very close, close enough.
ジジは絶対違うからね。シャワー。
Gigi is definitely wrong, though. Shower.
シャワーじゃないですよ。シャワシャワって。
It's not a shower. "Shawa shawa."
そう、さっきのピーの音のさ、ピー音の。
Right, like that peeing sound from earlier, the peeing sound.
いや、でも一応なんか理屈的にも間違ってないと思うすけどね。
Well, but logically speaking, I think it's not wrong either, though.
え？ジジがさ、だって、おしっこした後にさ、静かになるじゃん。
Eh? Because, like, after Gigi pees, it gets quiet, right?
あ、そうそうそう。
Ah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
だから、しゃー。
So, "shaa."
しゃー…ちょっと違うか。
"Shaa..." Wait, that's a bit different.
I was explaining your logic.
あ、オッケー、thank you.
Ah, okay, thank you.
ソー、You're defending me.
So you're defending me.
Yeah, I was defending you.
Got you, got you.
じゃ、続いて行きましょう。
Now then, let's move on.
続いて、え、とっても冷たい飲み物を表すオノマトペは何でしょうか？
Next, um, what is the onomatopoeia for an extremely cold drink?
What's the sound of an extremely cold drink?
飲み物…そう、あれ冷たい…
A drink... Right, that cold...
あれと、あれだけど、何々、に冷えたって言いますね。あれでしょう。
That and that, but it's like, chilled to [blank]. That must be it.
Cold drink.
I only have one word in my head again!
これもね、漫画に出てくるかもね。
This might also appear in manga, you know.
A bit manga.
わからない。
I don't know.
Image.
Image, what sound? What sound am I?
What do you have in mind? Just do it! Just do it!
I'm scared! No, it's okay!
ジジがなんかやばそうなやつが、体、そうなんです。
Gigi looks like she's in trouble, her body... yeah, exactly.
な、何を画こうとしてるの？ジジ、大丈夫？
Wh-What are you trying to draw, Gigi? Are you okay?
ジジ、大丈夫？大丈夫？大丈夫？
Gigi, are you okay? Are you okay? Are you okay?
でも、あれかな、ビールとかに結構言うかな？
But, I wonder, do they say it a lot for things like beer?
Beer use would be...
じゃ、行きますか。え、じゃ、よぴぴ。
Shall we go? Um, so, Yopipi.
はい。確か、キンキンななんとかのやつです。はい。
Yes. I'm pretty sure it's something like "kinkin." Yes.
えっと、この前スタジオで、誰かさんの、ホロメンが誰かさんが、あのマネージャーにキンキンな飲み物が欲しいですって言われた。
Um, recently at the studio, someone, a holomember, asked the manager, "I want a super cold drink."
おおー、なるほど。
Ooh, I see.
ちょうど夏の、夏ぐらいで、うーん、誰かさん、ちょっと忘れちゃったんだけど、スタジオでなんか聞いたことがあります。
It was around summer, um, I forgot who, but I heard about it at the studio.
ああ、キンキンね。
Ah, "kinkin."
オッケー。
Okay.
じゃあ、こぼ。
Next, Kobo.
Ah, so I felt like when you after you drink cold, a really cold drink, your uh after that your head will hurt and then you will say "atatata!"
ああ、なんか冷たいもの飲んだあとさ、頭痛くなるじゃないですか。その時に「あたたたた！」って。
Ah, like after you drink something cold, your head starts hurting, right? At that time, you're like, "atatata!"
なるほどね。だからこそ「あたたたた」って答えてました。
I see. That's why you answered "atatata."
あたたたた。オッケー、オッケー。あー、はいはい。
Atatata. Okay, okay. Ah, right, right.
じゃあ続いて、ジジ。
Next, Gigi.
Uh...
寒い！寒い！寒いでしょ？
Cold! Cold! It's cold, right?
寒い。Yes.
Cold. Yes.
寒い？寒い、うまい？寒い、うまい、うまい？可愛い。オッケー。寒い。寒い飲み物、オッケー？
Cold? Cold, delicious? Cold, delicious, delicious? Cute. Okay. Cold. Cold drink, okay?
はい。
Yes.
はい、おっけい。かわいい。
Okay, cute.
じゃあ続いて、ベチャ。
Then let's continue, Bae-chan.
なんか「き」から始まった気がした、もう忘れちゃった。
I feel like it started with "ki," but I forgot.
「き」から始まる、「き」「な」「ん」「ち」らな感じ。「き」、「き、き」。
It starts with "ki," "ki-," something like "ki," "ki, ki."
「き」、「き」「ね」。
"Ki," "ki-ne."
あ、「き」、「き」？おっけい「き」、「き」。
Ah, "ki," "ki"? Okay, "ki."
おっけいおっけいおっけい。「き」。
Okay, okay, okay. "Ki."
じゃあ、ラオラ。
Then, Raora.
あ、あ、えっさ、かんぱい！
Ah, it's a kanpai!
かんぱい！かんぱい！ちゃ、かんぱい！
Kanpai! Kanpai!
かんぱい！やった！いぇーい、かんぱい！
Kanpai! Let's go!
やった！いぇーい、いぇーい、いぇーい、いぇーい、いぇーい、レッツゴー！レッツゴー！
Okay, let's go! Let's go!
おっけい？かんぱい！
Okay? Kanpai!
じゃあ正解行きましょう。
Then let's go with the correct answer.
正解は、きんきんに冷えた飲み物でございますので、きんきんでございますね！
The correct answer is... a drink chilled to the max, so "kinkin" is it?
きんきん！よーく冷えててすごーい！
Kinkin, wow!
ゆた、ありがとう誰かさんの便利のね。
Yuta, thank you, Darekasan, for the convenience.
誰かさんありがとうございます、新しい、きんか、あ、きんきに。
Darekasan, thank you, it's a new "kinka," ah, "kinkini."
はい、きんきに、きんき、きんきん、きんきん。
Right, "kinkini," "kinki," "kinkin."
きんきんに冷えてやがるよっていうセリフがアニメにもありますねえ。
"Kinkin ni hieteagaru yo" is a line that's also in anime, right?
ほほほーい。はい。
Ho ho ho! Yes.
じゃあ続いては、えーと、行きますか。
Then next, shall we go?
続いてこちら。よいしょ。
Next is this one. Let's see.
キラキラ、星がキラキラしてるみたいな、キラキラのもっと強い表現。
"Kirakira," like stars sparkling, "kirakira," but an even stronger expression.
もっとキラキラ？
"Motto kirakira"?
もっとまぶしい？
"Motto mabushii"?
どう表現するでしょうか。
How would you express that?
あれ？これじゃなの？
Ah, is it this?
これは結構何パターンかある。
This has a couple of different variations.
あれ、なんだかのほにゃららの、えっと、ポケモン思い出しちゃって。
What's this? Some sort of...
おー。ポケモン。
Pokémon!
ポケモン？そっか。
Pokémon?
そ、そ、like、キラキラ、but upgrade、more stronger、yeah、like more、with more punch、キラキラ、more power.
So, like, "kirakira," but stronger, yeah, like more...
level up キラキラ。
Level up "kirakira."
level up キラキラ、powerful キラキラ。
Level up "kirakira," powerful "kirakira."
描いてくれるって、祭りを。
She's drawing a festival.
かわいい。
Cute.
I'm bribing the judge.
はい。
Right.
I'm bribing the judge! Why?
She's trying to bribe the judge.
I don't know the word.
なんかMCさんにワイロ送ってます。
She's offering a bribe to MC-san.
お？もう一回？
What? One more?
何々何？
What, what, what?
あの、知らないので、あの、MCにワイロ送ってます。
Because I don't know, I'm offering a bribe to MC.
ワイロ？
A bribe?
はい。
Yes.
あ、そういうこと？
Ah, is that what it is?
じゃあ、ヒントね、ヒント。
Then, hint, hint.
ヒントは、え、ホロライブメンバーの曲の歌詞に入ってますね。
The hint is that it's in the lyrics of a Hololive member's song.
もっと言うと、ホロライブメンバーの曲...
More specifically, it's in a Hololive member's song...
ねねちの、あの曲、「ねねちソング」、あー、に、入ってる。
in "Nenene Song," ah, no, "Nenene Song."
あとはキラキラの進化、キラキラパワーアップさせた感じかな？
Also, it's the evolution of "kirakira," like "kirakira" powered up.
おー、がヒント。
Ooh, that's a hint.
どうでしょうか。分かるかな？
How's that? Do you know?
おっけい？ワイロおっけい？
Okay, "wairo" okay?
ワイロは。
"Wairo" is...
え、これ、ワイロくれるの誰？
Wait, who gave the "wairo"?
誰がくれるの？
Who's giving it?
ジジ？いや、ラオラ？ジジかな。
Jiji? No, Raora?
ジジ？むり？ジジジジジジジ。
Jiji? Jiji, Jiji?
あ、ジジじゃあ、ワイロとして、あの、very cute and voice please、まつりおねえちゃん、おっけい？
Ah, Jiji, as a bribe, please give us a very cute and polite festival, Onee-chan, okay?
たぶんね、その、あの映画のワイロの話を。
About that... the "wairo" talk in that movie.
あ、そういう？
Ah, is that so?
あるいはゆづき、ゆづき。
Or maybe Yuzuki? Yuzuki?
「きだい！きだい！」、「まっちゅじ！おねえさん！」、「キラキラ！」
"Kida! Kida!" "Mattsu-ni! Onee-san!" "Kirakira!"
大好き！
I love it!
きしょく悪っ！やば！
Awful!
かわいい！
Cute!
あ、ジジ、あの、you name word、ヒント、ね、you name word。
Ah, Jiji, um, "you name word" hint, "you name word"?
Your name is?
My name is a hint? It is.
おっけい？
Okay?
あ、あ、あれね。
Ah, that, right?
で、え、あ、でも、うん、ま、ま、ま、ねねちの曲にも入ってるよと。
And, well, um, it's also in Nenene's song.
おっけー。いけるかな?
Okay. Can we do it?
おっけー。じゃあ聞いてこ。
Okay. Then let's go listen.
じゃあ、よぴぴから。
Then, starting with Yopipi.
はい。えっと、きらん。なんか、キラキラとかさ、そういうの?
Yes. Um, "kiran." Like, "kira-kira," stuff like that?
うんうんうん。かなと思って、でも今思ってたらあれだなと思ってて。
Yeah, yeah, yeah. I thought so, but now thinking about it, I realized...
おっ。
Oh.
聞けますか?
Can we hear it?
あ、いや、大丈夫です。
Ah, no, it's fine.
でもなんか、そう、なんかそのキラキラもっと強いのが、なんかいつもの対応?対応だから、あ、
But like, yeah, like for "kira-kira," something stronger, like the usual Taiou? Because it's Taiou, ah
あ、対応ピピってなっちゃうんじゃないですか?
Ah, wouldn't it become "Taiou Pipi"?
対応によく使われるものかな?
Is it something often used for Taiou?
なるほど。
I see.
はいはいはいはい。
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
じゃあ、こぶちゃん。
Then, Kobuchan.
かわいいですね。
How cute.
Cuz I heard someone saying, uh... Pokémon? Uh-huh, uh-huh.
So I think like... Pika Pika!
Pika Pika, uh... okay.
確かに強い。確かに強いピカピカは。
It's definitely strong. "Pika-pika" is definitely strong.
確かに。ピカピカ強い。
Definitely. Pika-pika is strong.
ストロング、ストロングピカピカ。
Strong, strong pika-pika.
じゃあ、じじ。
Then, Jiji.
じじもりん!キラキラ!ぎらぎら!
Jiji morin! Kira-kira! Gira-gira!
ぎらぎら
Gira-gira
天才じゃん!
You're a genius!
買収されたわ!最高!
You were bought off! Awesome!
ピカピカちょっと惜しくて、それがね、ビカビカとかだったら世界、
Pika-pika was a bit close, and if that were bika-bika or something, the world—
あ、ビビカ?
Ah, bibika?
もっと、まぶし、まぶしいね。
Even more blindingly bright, right?
あ、ピカピカの方が強いんだ?
Ah, pika-pika is stronger?
そう。ピカピカはまあキラキラと同じくらいか?
Right. Pika-pika is about the same as kira-kira?
ええ?
Eh?
なるほど、ちょっと弱いかな?ピカピカ、ギラギラ。
I see, maybe a bit weaker? Pika-pika, gira-gira.
Pika Pika is on the same level as Kira Kira.
あ、でもっそっか、いつも聞いてるのはなんかギラギラ太陽なんとかっていう
Ah, but wait, the one we always listen to is something like "gira-gira taiyou"...
音乃瀬のね、あのギラファもね、ギラファ、ファーミーティング、ギラファとかもね、ほんと、同じ感じで、明るいまぶしい、みたいな
Otonose's, um, Giraffa too, y'know, Giraffa, Far Meeting, Giraffa, etc., really, in the same way, bright, blinding, something like that...
Driving works? I could drive. I mean, I could drive. Okay, nice, nice, nice, nice info.
続いて、同じ感じでございますけども、心臓のこの音、どきどき、をもっと強く表現すると
Continuing with a similar feel, but for the sound of the heart, dokidoki, if we express it even stronger...
ストロンガー、ドキドキ?
Stronger dokidoki?
ドキドキ。
Dokidoki.
ベターゼン、ドキドキ?
Better than dokidoki?
ドキ?あれ?これもの、なんか何パターンかあるから、合ってたら大丈夫なんだけど。
Doki? Huh? Since there are several patterns of this, it's fine if it matches.
どっちでもいって感じですか?そしたら。まあ、2つ3つくらい表現はあるかな?
So either way is fine? Then. Well, there are maybe two or three expressions?
ドクン?
Dokun?
どきどきね、どきどきどきどき。ドキ?ドキドキ、ドキドキ。
Dokidoki, y'know, dokidoki dokidoki. Doki? Dokidoki, dokidoki.
ドキンと強く、強く。強く。
Dokinto, strongly, strongly. Strongly.
ねぇちゃん、ちょっと次のヒントは
Ne-chan, for the next hint...
教えないにゃ
I won't tell you~
あ、ひとつだけいいからおねぇちゃん
Ah, just one hint, please, Ne-chan!
おまいがー
Oh my god!
めっちゃこれヒントだけど
Well, here's a huge hint:
うーん、まぁ、強調するのに日本でわ結構ちっちゃい「っ」を入れたりとか
Um, well, to emphasize it, in Japanese we add a small "tsu,"
あ！あと、わくわくです！
Ah! Also, like "wakuwaku"!
そうですね、あと言葉を変えるんだったら
Right. Or if you change the word,
あの、なんだろ、なんだろな、大きな、大きな音っぽいというか
um, what is it, something that sounds like a big, loud sound,
まぁどうもね、大きそうだけどね
well, it sounds big anyway.
はい、そんな感じですかね
Yeah, something like that.
あい、ありがとうおねぇちゃん
Thank you, Ne-chan!
うおお！うおお！
Whoa! Whoa!
よしよしよし
Okay, okay, okay!
いや、完全にぶらぶ MC
No, totally grabbed the MC!
おっけー、おっけー、おっけー
Okay, okay, okay!
じゃ、Kジーシワースタート！
Then, KG Simas start!
Why are you grabbing me, MC?
さあ、じゃあ、よぴって行きますか？
Well, shall we go with Yopi?
はい！ドックンです！
Yes! Dokkun!
はい、ドックン、ドックン、ドックン、ドックン、ドックン、ドックン、ドックン
Yes, dokkun, dokkun, dokkun...
え、じゃあカバー
Um, then Cover-
I remember to mock Zeta about a part of her original song lyrics,
it's "babu babu" but it's actually "baku baku baku" or "baku baku baku"...
yeah, something like that. "baku baku, baku baku, baku"
じゃあ、続いてじーじ
Next, Gigi-
え、うま娘、ドキドキドキ、ドキーン、ドキーン
Um, Uma Musume, doki doki doki, doki-n, doki-n!
あ、ドキーン、戻る！
Ah, doki-n, back!
はい、はい、はい、はい、なるほど、確かに
Yes, yes, yes, yes, I see, indeed.
じゃあ、べーちゃん
Then, Bae-chan:
いやもう、ドキドキをもっと強くして、もはや心臓発作
Well, make the heartbeat even stronger, to the point of a heart attack!
どどどどどどどどどどどどどどどどどど、ハードアタック、コンバンドどどどどどどどねちゃん
Dododododododo... hard attack, command dodododododo, Ne-chan!
はい、じゃあ、ラオーラ
Yes, then Raora:
えーとさ、バクン、バクン
Um, bakun, bakun!
あ、バクン、バクン、バクン、バクン、バクン、バクン、バクン
Ah, bakun, bakun, bakun, bakun...
I was listening recently, so it must be this. Wait, everyone is different, though.
じゃあ、正解、正解者は、ん？
So, the correct answer, who is the winner? Hmm?
これね、全員正解でいいかなと思います
I think everyone gets it right!
おお、みんな正解！やったー！
Oh, everyone's right! Yay!
そう、結構いろんな表現があって、へえ
Yes, there are quite a few different expressions, huh.
まぁ、ドキーンとか、ドキンドックンとか、うん、ドキドキ、ドキドキとか、ドキドキね、うん、
Well, doki-n, dokin-dokkun, um, doki-doki, doki-doki, doki-doki, um,
どどどどど、強そう、死んでるよ
dododododo, sounds strong, you're dying!
死んでる死んでる、緊張してる時とかにどどどどどっするんだよね、はいはい、とゆーことで全員正解、素晴らしい！やったー！
You're dying, dying! When you're nervous, you go dododododo, right, right. So everyone's right, wonderful! Yay!
じゃあちょっと、今度は上図、上図
Now, next is the upper diagram/skill? "jouzu" (skilled)
今度は、今からとあるサウンドを聞いてもらいます
Next, you'll listen to a certain sound,
あの、チャンネルにね、ボイスを貼りますので、聞く。あ、ほうほう。これ何と言っているのだろうかという問題でございますね。
um, we'll post the voice clip in the channel, so listen. Ah, I see. The question is, what are they saying?
なんと言っているか？
What are they saying?
今がセミの鳴き声を送ります。
We will now send a cicada's cry.
なんと言っているでしょうか、セミは。
What is the cicada saying?
Alright, they've sent... she sent a little voice clip. What is this cicada saying in the voice clip?
Okay, then, let's let the listeners hear it as well. Here it is.
Also, we have to come up with the onomatopoeia, naruhodo ne. From listening to it... Ah, it's in the chat, it's in the chat.
はい、これは何となるほど、なるほど。
Yes, what is this... I see, I see.
はははははは。So what is that sound that the cicada is making? Haha.
Ha-ha-ha-ha. So what is that sound that the cicada is making? Haha.
日本人だったらね、絶対にわかるね。
If you're Japanese, you'd definitely understand.
How do you... Chichichi... Chara-chika? How do you pronounce it? Cicada? Chichica? Cicada? Cicada?
Enchilada! Enchilada! Enchilada! I thought it was cicada.
What does it look like? Cicada? Cicada? Cicada?
Oh, I see, I see. It has big wings. Yeah!
ほう、聞いたことない
"Hou, I've never heard it before."
聞いたことある、家で、家、そこら中…
"I've heard it all the time inside... everywhere!"
セミ？
"Cicadas?"
いや、聞いたことある
"No, I've heard them everywhere."
で、降って、もう鳴かない
"They fall down and can't chirp anymore."
これ分かったら
"If you get this right,"
J.P.やね
"it's definitely JP."
さすがにセミ…本物の？
"Naturally... Is it a real cicada?"
あ、セミ聞いたことないんです
"Ah, I've never heard a real cicada."
え？いないの？
"Eh? They're not there?"
いや、いるとは思なんだけど、声は聞こえるけど、姿が…
"Well, I thought they were there, and I can hear their voices, but I have no idea where they actually are."
そうなんだ、え、子供の頃セミ取りとかしないの？
"Is that so? Eh, when you were a kid, didn't you catch cicadas?"
ない。
"No."
あ、あれは多分、インドネシアのなんか、日本文化的な…へえ、そうなんだ
"Ah, that's probably like, Indonesian... Japanese cultural thing... Oh, is that so?"
じゃあ、セミの種類とか言われても分かんないのか
"Then if they tell you the type of cicada, you wouldn't know?"
わかんない、全員セミだもん
"I don't know, they're all just cicadas!"
全員セミだもん、ええー
"They're all cicadas! Eeh?!"
そうなんだ。
"Is that so."
Anyone of you guys caught cicadas before?
No.
I got one in my balcony.
Your balcony? It was huge! It was like super big.
And it was super loud, but on the veranda...
ベランダにいる？こんなに大きいの？セミって？
"They're on the veranda? Are cicadas this big? Cicadas, they're pretty huge."
マジ？怖くね？
"Seriously? Isn't it scary?"
いや、大丈夫じゃない？
"No, isn't it fine?"
大丈夫じゃない！何回も聞いていいよ、大丈夫じゃない？
"It's NOT fine! You can listen as many times as you want, isn't it not fine?"
大丈夫じゃない。
"It's not fine."
Give me have hint, hint, give me hint!
"Give me a hint, hint, give me a hint!"
なんかあの、ショワショワショワって言ってるのは無視していい。
"You can ignore the ones going 'shuwa shuwa shuwa'."
その、大きい、低めの音の、セミさんはなんて言ってるからねえ。
"As for the big, lower-pitched cicada... listen to what it's saying."
Focus on the lowest sounding notes, ignore the shuwa shuwa in the background.
"Focus on the lowest-sounding notes, ignore the shuwa shuwa in the background."
困ってるね。ネ、オッケーオッケー。
"You're in trouble, huh? Ne, okay okay."
じゃあ、行きましょう、ヨピピから。
"Then let's go, starting with Yopi."
はい、みー、みーってなん……みーみーはい、みーね、オッケー。
"Hai, mi-, mi- what... mi- mi- hai, mi- ne, okay."
じゃあコボちゃん。
"Then Kobo-chan."
じい……じい！可愛い、じいじいじい！
"Gii... gii! Cute, gii gii gii!"
じいだね！可愛い！はい、じゃあじじ。
"It's gii! Cute! Hai, then Jiji."
じじは、じじじじ……じじじじじじ！じじの声！
"Jiji is, jiji jiji... jiji jiji jiji! Jiji's voice!"
じゃあ続いてべちゃ。
"Then next, Becha."
えー、ういー！ういー！ういー！オッケーオッケー。
"Ee, ui-! ui-! ui-! Okay okay."
じゃあラストララ。あ、クリックリッックリッ！可愛い、クリックリッ！
"Then last, Lala. Ah, clik clik clik! Cute, clik clik!"
じゃあ正解行きましょう。正解は……
"Then let's go to the correct answer. The correct answer is..."
はい、みー、みみみみんで……ヨピピ正解！
"Hai, mi-, mimimimin... Yopipi is correct!"
みみん、みみみって聞こえるみん……
"Mimiminn, it sounds like 'min' and..."
みみって聞こえないんだよね？
"Wait, it doesn't sound like 'mi', does it?"
M、M放送なくない？Mのサウンド……
"M, isn't there no M broadcast? M sound..."
このセミの名前がそもそもミンミンゼミという名前のセミでね。
"This cicada's name is originally the 'minminzemi'."
みんみんぜみって、日本人には聞こえてますね。
"Japanese people hear it as 'minminzemi'."
じゃあ続いて、ネクストセミ行きますよ。
"Then next, let's go to the next cicada."
ネクストセミ？え、どんな感じのサウンド？
"Next cicada? Eh, what kind of sound?"
ワンモアセミ、行きます。
"One more cicada, let's go."
ワンモアセミ、セミ2、こちらです。
"One more cicada, cicada 2, here it is."
(Cicada 2 sound)
[Cicada 2 chirping loudly]
はいはい、めっちゃ聞こえますね。多分日本人にはめちゃめちゃ聞こえる。
"Hai hai, you can hear it very clearly. Probably Japanese people can hear it extremely well."
聞こえる？Where's that sound from?
"You can hear it? Where's that sound from?"
I don't know.
What the heck?
セミバージョン2ですよ。
"It's cicada version 2."
Mating Call
[Whiteboard: Mating Call]
セミ2ね？ヒントお願いします！
"Cicada 2, right? Hint please!"
このセミ鳴き声は？
This cicada mating call...
ね。
Let's see.
あの、タタタタタン、タタタタタンって言うのが鳴き声。
You know, when they make that sound like "tatatatatan"
タタタタタン、タタタタタン、
that repeats...
が、日本人にはタタタタタン、だからまあ5文字くらいかな？
For Japanese people, it's about 5 characters long?
ん？ん？
Hmm?
5？
Five?
音で探すんだ、そのパターン。
Finding the sound pattern.
パターン？
Pattern?
ヒント難しいね、これは。
Hints are hard, this is.
ヒントとしてはむずいな。
As a hint, it's pretty tough.
ちょっとタタタタタンも擬音語だよって言われたらもうごめんなさい、それはもう
If you tell me "tatatatatan" is an onomatopoeia, then I'm sorry, that's...
ええ？
Eh?
むずっ。
Difficult...
タタタタタタタタタタしかもうしてない。
It's just "tatatatatan" over and over!
タタタタタタタタ
Tatatatatata...
うーん、Eievui？
Hmm, Eevee?
7文字だよ。
7 characters.
7文字だよ、文字数！
It's seven characters!
みぎわめ？
Migiwame?
文字数！文字数！
Wait, no, it's 7 characters!
もじ、文字数、文字数！
Wait, 7 letters!
みぎわめ？
Migiwame?
文字数ね。
Wait, no.
まあ、伸ばし棒が入ります、あと、最後のほうに。
Well, there's a prolonged sound at the end, right near the end.
え？
Eh?
伸ばし棒。
Elongated sound.
で、7文字。
And 7 characters.
伸ばすと？
Elongate...
伸ばすと7文字ですね。
Elongate and it's 7 characters, right?
え？
Eh?
あの、無編集の流しとくか。
Ah, I should just play the unedited audio.
難しいね。
It's hard, isn't it?
難しいね、難しい。
It is, it is.
このリズム、自体はわかるんだけどどう書いていいかわかんない。
This rhythm, I understand how it goes, but how to write it is what's hard.
落ち着く。
It's calming...
この声を聞くと落ち着きますよ、夏だなあって。
Hearing this voice makes you feel calm, like, "Ah, it's summer."
え？
Eh?
違うよ、プクプクプクプクじゃなくて。
Is it not Pukukupuku?
ポケモン？
Pokemon?
ポケモンっぽい。
It sounds like a Pokemon.
プクプク、プクプクピーカ。
Pukukupuku.
じゃあ行きましょうか、Yoppippiから。
Okay, let's go with Yoppippi first.
いや、プクプクプクプクじゃないですか？セミversion 2？
It's not "pukukukukuku", right? Cicada version 2?
セミversion 2？
Cicada version 2?
プクプク？
Pukukuku?
プクプクプクプクで、青い。
Pukukukuku, right? Blue?
オッケー、オッケー。
Okay, okay.
じゃあ、こむちゃん。
Next, Komu-chan.
えっと、そう、the previous one was mingming, right? うん、あは。
So, the previous one was "mingming", right? Uh-huh.
And, uh, I heard...
this is more than mingming, so it's...
a mating call like maengmaeng, maengmaeng, maengmaeng!
ちょっと待って。
Hold on a minute.
そもそも、なんで you wrote mating call?
First of all, why did you write "mating call"?
えっと、QIの鳴き声 maengmaeng です。
Um, QI's cry is "maengmaeng".
あ、でも QI の鳴き声なんだよね、実際。
Ah, but that's QI's cry, right? Actually.
あ、そうなの？
Is that so?
あ、そう、yes! だからそこは正解。Because it is a mating call!
Oh, yes! So that's why it is a mating call!
Is it? Oh my god! Oh my god!
It is a mating call! Oh my god!
Oh my god!
セミのオスが、あの、メス来テーって言ってる時の
When male cicadas say "it's female time,"
声だから、そこは正しい。QIだよね？
that voice, so that's correct, QI, right?
Oh my god! Oh my god!
Oh my god!
え、でも、でも maengmaeng が正しいかどうかるね。
Wait, is "maengmaeng" correct or not?
あ、そう maengmaeng ね。オッケー。
Ah, so "maengmaeng", right? Okay.
Whether it's maengmaeng or not.
相が聞いて、Gigi。
Let's go with Gigi.
ジリ、ジリ、ジリ、ジリ。
Trrrrrg! Trrrrrg!
はい、オッケー。ジリ、ジリ、ジリ、ジリ、オッケーね。
Okay, trrrrrg, right? Okay.
じゃあ、ベチャ。
Then, Becha.
え？なんか。
Eh? Something like...
プクプクプクプク！プクプクプクプク！
Pukukukuku! Pukukukuku!
ポケモンっぽい音だけど。
It sounds like Pokémon.
ポケモン、ポケモンみたい。
It's like Pokémon.
オッケー。
Okay.
プクプク、プクプクピカか。
Pukukuku, pukukupukaka.
オッケー。
Okay.
じゃあラオーラ。
Then, Raora.
Yomapinyun, it's a cricket.
And a cricket sounds like...
プリンク、プリンク、プリンク、プリンク。
Pring pring pring pring pring!
プリンク、プリンク、可愛い。
Pring pring, cute.
プリンク、プリンクね。
Pring pring.
プリンク、プリンク。
プイクピイク？
Pukukuku.
じゃあ、いきます。
Then, let's go.
こちらの鳴き声はツクツクボウシでございます。
This crying voice is "tsukutsukuboshi".
はい！
Hai!
待って、なんで？なんで？なんで？なんで？なんで？
Wait, why? Why? Why? Why?
なんで、Why? ツクツクボウシ！ツクツクボウシ！ツクツクボウシ！
Why is it tsukutsukuboshi? Tsukutsukuboshi!
So I should do this if I want to mating call someone?
待って、待って、待って、待って。実際、can you please?
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, actually...
Like that?
Nottogigi? Nottogigi?
QIの鳴き声？No, no, no, no.
QI's cry? No, no, no, no.
ツクツクボウシ！ツクツクボウシ！ヤバい、ヤバい、ヤバい、ヤバい、Shut up, please!
Tsukutsukuboshi! Tsukutsukuboshi! It's dangerous, dangerous, dangerous, dangerous, please!
学んでしまった。
Manandeshimata.
はい。
Right.
まあ、ツクツクボウシかツクツクホシ、どっちでもオッケーです。
Well, "tsukutsukuboshi" or "tsukutsukuhoshi", either is okay.
ツクツクホシ？
Tsukutsuku hoshi?
どっちでもオッケーです。
Either is okay.
ツクツクホシ？
Tsukutsuku hoshi?
ツクツクホシ止まっております。
Tsukutsuku hoshi has stopped.
ちょっとね、これセミは難しいですね。
Well, this cicada is difficult, right?
セミの種類とかは関係ないんですか？
Does it have anything to do with the type of cicada?
あ、これはツクツクボウシっていうセミの鳴き声ですね、今は。
Well, this is a cicada called "tsukutsukuboshi".
あ、種類？
The type?
そう、種類もツクツクボウシっていう名前のセミ。
So the type is also a cicada named "tsukutsukuboshi".
ちなみに他にも、さっきのがミンミンゼミだったでしょ？
By the way, besides that, the previous one was mingmingzemi, right?
アブラゼミっていうのが、あの、ジジがさっき言ってたジジジジジジジジって鳴くのがアブラゼミ。
Aburazemi is what Gigi was saying, "jijijijijiji".
…ゼミだったり…
...cicadas and such...
アブラゼミ？
Oil cicada?
はい。
Yes.
日本人だったらセミの声を聞くだけで、何のセミか分かります。
If you're Japanese, just by hearing the cicada's cry, you know what kind it is.
え？
Eh?
わあ、すごーい。
Wow, amazing!
They can differentiate what kind of cicada it is depending on what it sounds like.
There's different enchiladas...
enchilada—yeah, so what we heard were two different enchiladas is GG.
So you're saying that there is an enchilada that says GG?
GG, yes.
ジジジ。
Jijiji.
え？ 3種類って何の名前だっけ？
Eh? What were the three types called again?
えと、3種類の…ジジジ。ジジジはアブラゼミですね。
Um, of the three... Jijiji. Jijiji is the oil cicada.
アブラゼミ。はい、アブラゼミ、アブラゼミ。
Oil cicada. Yes, oil cicada, oil cicada.
アブラゼミ、はい、アブラゼミ。
Oil cicada, yes, oil cicada.
Ah, large brown cicada. Hmm, large brown cicada, goes...
なるほど。なるとほー。なるほど、なるほど。
I see. I see. I see, I see.
続いて、ラスト問題。
Moving on to the last question.
あ、ラスト！
Ah, last!
これ、めっっちゃ、ちょっとジャパニーズすぎる、難しいと思うんですけど。
This is super, a bit too Japanese, I think it's difficult, but...
これ解けたら、もういついつ日本に来ても戦えます。
If you solve this, you can fight whenever you come to Japan.
誰だっけ？
Who was it again?
え、日本には独特な、これにしか使えないオノマトペがあります。
Eh, Japan has a unique onomatopoeia used only for this.
桃が川から流れてくるオノマトペは何でしょう？
What is the onomatopoeia for a peach flowing down a river?
What is the onomatopoeia for when a peach comes flowing down the river?
Sliding away?
桃太郎を呼んでないんだったら、これ桃太郎呼んでないんだったらできないじゃないですか、これ桃太郎。
If you're not calling Momotaro, you can't do this, right, Momotaro.
これ、これ分かったら、もう日本に来ていただいていつでも…
If you figure this out, come to Japan anytime...
What is the sound that a peach makes when it flows down the river? It's a very, very specific onomatopoeia. I'm guessing if you know the story...
テカ、きたないよ。
Teca, that's dirty.
Is it folklore? Yeah, you know the Momotaro, the Momotaro, peach boy.
We gotta guess, we gotta guess. 桃にしか使わないですね。リンゴとかが変わりに出てても使わない。
We gotta guess, we gotta guess. It's only used for peaches. Even if apples or something floated by instead, we wouldn't use it.
I only use it for peaches, it's only peaches.
I'm sure this is gonna be really weird. 桃太郎呼んでないんだらわかんないやつ。
I'm sure this is gonna be really weird. If you didn't call Momotaro, you wouldn't get it.
桃太郎一回読んだんだよね。おっしゃ、わかるじゃん。
You read Momotaro once, right? Then you know.
Maybe I know that legend-boy. Ah, cuz I watched...
If you read the actual book, it's written in the actual book, like in Japanese. So if you haven't read it, then you probably don't know.
桃の中かと思ってた。
I thought it was inside the peach.
確か前にあの雑談配信で、これのことちょっと語った気がする。
I feel like I talked about this before on a zatsudan stream.
そうなんだ！そう、なんでこうなったのって言われたらわかんないって。
Oh, is that so! Yeah, if you ask why it became like this, I don't know.
すごい、でも話すんだ。昔話ね。
But amazing, it tells a story. A folklore tale, you know.
なんだっけ？これはね、多分知らないと本当に当てられないと思うけど。
What was it? This, I think if you don't know, you really can't guess.
日本人だったらあのちっちゃい子からおじいちゃんおばあちゃんまでみんな分かるからね。桃の川流れてる音なんだって。
If you're Japanese, from little kids to grandpas and grandmas, everyone knows it. It's the sound of a peach flowing down a river.
じゃあ行きましょうか。最終問題。じゃあ、よぴぴ、どうでしょう？
Alright, let's go. Final question. Yopipi, what do you think?
はい、どんぶらこです。はい、どんぶらこ、どんぶらこ、オッケー。
Yes, domburako. Yes, domburako, domburako, okay.
じゃあこぼちゃん。お尻？もぐもぐもぐ。
Then Kobo-chan. Butt? Mogu mogu mogu.
お尻みたい、流れてるのお尻みたいね。
It looks like an ass, flowing like an ass.
If I saw a huge peach floating in the water and it was like a really big peach and it was huge...
じゃあ、べちゃーん。よなか…どんぴしゃっ！
Then, betchaan. Middle of... bullseye!
どんぴしゃ！水の音？水の音…どんぴしゃ。
Dompisha! Sound of water? Sound of water... dompisha.
Maybe it's puka puka. Ah, puka puka! Kawaii. Puka puka.
じゃあ、正解行きましょう。
Well then, let's go to the correct answer.
どんぶらこ、
Donburako,
どんぶらこ。
donburako.
どんぶらこ、
Donburako,
どんぶらこ！
donburako!
Oh my god.
なぜです？
Why is that?
なぜ川は、
Why is it?
そうやって本に書いてあるからね。
Because that's how it's written in the book!
理由は無い。
Is there no reason?
理由は無い？無い、無い、無いよ。
Is there no reason? None, none, none.
そう、聞こえるの？
Oh, so that's how it sounds?
だって本に書いてあるからね。うん、そう。
Because it's written like that in the book, right?
で、あれだね、ぷかぷかは、あの浮いてるもの、水に浮いてたらぷかぷかで合ってる。
And puka-puka is for things floating in the water.
おおー！
Oh!
それで、もし浮いてる、
So if it's floating...
水に浮いてたらぷかぷかで合ってる。
If it's floating in the water, it's puka-puka.
どんぶらこ、どんぶらこ。
Donburako, donburako.
そう、んで桃が川から流れてくるときはどんぶらこ、ですね。
So when a peach comes flowing down a river, it's donburako.
じゃあ、りんごだったら？あ、りんごだったらぷかぷか。
What if it's an apple? If it's an apple, it's puka-puka.
Oh my god!
桃only donburako.
Peach only donburako.
ということでね、えー、皆さま、
And with that, everyone...
WHY JAPAN?
オノマトペ。
Japan and its onomatopoeia.
でも、可愛いかったのでね。
Even so, it's so cute.
あ、で、ちなみにオノマトペではないんですけど、
And by the way, not that it's an onomatopoeia,
今日みんなにじゃあ、えー、覚えてってほしい言葉があります。
today I want to teach you all a word.
えー、全然わかんない。全然わかんないっていうのを日本語では、ちんぷんかんぷんって言いますね。
When you have no idea what's going on, in Japanese it's called "chinputsukanputs.
ちんぷんかんぷん！わ、可愛い。ちんぷんかんぷん！はい、ちんぷんかんぷん！ぷん！ぷん！ちんぷんかんぷん！
Chinpunkanpun! Oh, so cute! Chinpunkanpun!
ちんぷんかんぷん。
Chinpunkanpun.
JAPAN…
So, Japan...
JAPAN WHY??
When you have no idea
of anything, this is the onomatopoeia you use.
when you have no idea about anything, this is the onomatopoeia you use.
ちんぷんかんぷん！
Chinpunkanpun!
うん、I like that, I like that.
I like that, I like that.
I'm very scared of you using this phrase, Gg.
Every time someone asks me something, "Chinpunkanpun!"
I'm just scared of you forgetting what the full phrase is.
なんか素敵な言葉ですよ、ちんぷんかんぷんが。
It's such a cute phrase, "Chinpunkanpun."
はい、ちんぷんかんぷんですね。
"Chinpunkanpun," yes.
俺がちょっと、うん。
I'm kind of...
なんか怖いな、なんかちんぷんかんぷんのって言うオノマトペをね、
I feel a bit scared, you know.
全部その、覚えられない時だ、あの、忘れば、
When you can't remember it...
覚えられなくてGgがさ、怖いんだよね。覚えて、ちんぷんかんぷん、漢字もあるからね、ちんぷんかんぷんって。
You're just scared that you'll forget "Chinpunkanpun" and just say "Chinpunkanpun."
え、漢字もあるの？
Oh, there are kanji?
そう、漢字もあります、ちんぷんかんぷん。
Yes, there are kanji.
カタカナじゃなくて、カタカナね、ゆったり、ひらがなで言うことが多いけど、ちゃんとね、漢字がある。
It's katakana, but people usually write it in hiragana,
漢字が、そう、漢字があるんです。え、漢字あるの？
There are kanji? Yes, there are kanji.
なのでね、ちんぷんかんぷん、今きっと、そう。
So, "Chinpunkanpun"...
むず、むず、読めない、むず。
Wait, I can't read it!
コメントでね書いてくれてるけどさ。
People are writing it in the comments!
何これ？それがちんぷんかんぷんですね。
What's this? That's "Chinpunkanpun."
珍しい。
That's rare.
珍しいコーナー、何？漢字の、な、なんだっけ、おにょにょらのー、おぷん？
A rare corner...
うん、ちんぷんかんぷん、ですね。
"Chinpunkanpun," yes.
でもめっちゃ可愛いから、もし日本語わかんなくなったら、あ、日本語ちんぷんかんぷんですって言ったら、もうOK。
It's so cute, so if you ever don't understand Japanese anymore...
すべて解決！
Everything is solved!
OK、OK！やった！
OK. OK!
OK！
OK!
ということでね、えー、
And with that...
ちんぷんかんぷん、One onomatopoeia that おかゆsenpai taught me once.
"Chinpunkanpun," one onomatopoeia that Okayu-senpai taught me once.
おー！
Oh!
おかゆ先輩に教えてくれたオノマトペがあります。
There is an onomatopoeia Okayu-senpai taught me.
なんですか？
What is it?
え、え、ぶるんぶるんです。
It's "burun-burun"!
ぶる、ぶるんぶるん？ぶるんぶるんは、
Burun-burun? "Burun-burun" is...
おっぱいを、おっぱいを揺らすときの音。
The sound of shaking your breasts!
Oh my god!
ぶるんぶるん。
Burun-burun.
おー！
Oh!
え、ぶるんぶるん？
Eh, burun-burun?
ボインボインだよね、ボインボインも合ってる？ボインボイン、ボインボイン、ぶるんぶるん、OK。
Boin-boin is... "Boin-boin" is also good, right?
合ってる、両方おっぱい。
Both "boin" are correct.
で、もっと大きなおっぱいだと、バインバインになります。
And for even bigger breasts, it becomes "bain-bain"!
バインバイン！
Bain-bain!
もっと、もっと大きい
Even bigger...
おっぱいはバインバイン。
Breasts are "bain-bain."
バインバイン。
Bain-bain.
それ以上の大きいのはないですか？
Is there anything bigger than that?
それ以上大きいのないね。
There's nothing bigger than that.
たぶんバインバインが一番大きい。
"Bain-bain" is the biggest.
なるほど。
I see.
はい。
Okay.
今日の一優勝者 一応発表しますか。
Shall we announce today's overall winner?
今日はですね、やぴぴが優勝でございます。
Today, Yapipi is the winner!
もう、ほぼ！やったーー！
Almost! Yay!
すごい！半分以上正解して。
Amazing! You got more than half right.
いや、さす…天使だ！さすがでございますね。
Well, as... an angel! As expected.
いやいや、日本語上図。
No, no, your Japanese is good.
日本語上図、でもねえっと、他のメンバーも
Your Japanese is good, but you know, the other members too
あれですよ、半分は正解してますから、素晴らしいでございます。
Well, half of them got it right, so that's wonderful.
わあ、やったー！
Yay!
ということで、え、皆さん、本日もありがとうございました。
And with that, everyone, thank you very much for today as well.
え、チャンネル登録もね、あ、てこてこ、ありがとうございます。ありがと、ありがとね。
And channel subscriptions too... ah, tekoteko, thank you very much. Thanks, thanks.
あ、ありがと。サンキュー、ありがとサンキュー！
Ah, thanks. Thank you, thank you!
じゃあチャンネル登録も
Well, channel subscriptions too
え、ポチッとおねがいしますね。
Please click that button.
はい、ポチッとおねがいします。
Yes, please click it.
じゃあ最後はバイバイで終わっていきますよ。
Well, we'll end with a 'bye-bye'.
せーの。
Ready, set.
バイバーイ！サンキュー！チーパンプ！チーパンプ！チーパンプ！
Bye-bye! Thank you! Chiipanpu! Chiipanpu! Chiipanpu!